<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Adoption of Open-Source software&apos;s in Libraries in Digital Era: A Case Study of Pakistan</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Shehzad</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
							<email>shehzad_ecp@yahoo.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Muhammad</forename><surname>Ibrahim</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Sajjad</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Abid</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Peshawar Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Edwardes College Peshawar</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Riphah International University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Islamabad</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Library and Information Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Peshawar</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Allama Iqbal Open University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Islamabad</settlement>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Adoption of Open-Source software&apos;s in Libraries in Digital Era: A Case Study of Pakistan</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">96CDEFA33AF386105D77D317A93CC6F4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2026-03-09T17:01+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=false, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Open-Source Software</term>
					<term>Library Software Adoption</term>
					<term>Academic Libraries</term>
					<term>Pakistan</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This study aims to explore the adoption of Open-Source Software's (OSS) in the academic libraries of Pakistan. It also focuses on the challenges encountered during the application and management of these software's in both public and private sectors academic libraries around the country. Quantitative data was collected through structured questionnaire developed and distributed online to the target population. The findings indicate that the library's adoption of OSS, such as Koha, SLIMS, GREENSTONE, and DSpace, was motivated by the need to distribute information to library users efficiently, modernize library staff workflows, and enhance user accessibility to library information resources. The OSS has been instigated specially in the cataloguing and circulation and digital library management functions of the library. The major hurdles impeding the software's full implementation include lack of planning, lack of technical expertise, and security concerns related to library software's. Study recommends that, to successfully adopt and implement any integrated library Software, proper planning and prior feasibility studies, along with proper training of the library professionals are recommended.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>In this information age, the information has become an essential element for survival and vital as air we breathe. The advent of information technology (IT) has truly transformed the whole world into a global village and in real sense has affected every aspect of our lives <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Hussain &amp; Ahmad, 2021)</ref>. The Information Technologies (IT) particularly, computer programs and software's also played a significant role in information management. This unbelievable technology of computers software's has enabled us to access, collect, organize, preserve and disseminate information from one point at library. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Palmer and Choi (2014)</ref> stated that adopting new technologies is a nonstop challenge that academic libraries must agree to take. The history shows that among the institutions, libraries were quick to embrace IT during its early stages of development. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Asim and Mairaj (2019)</ref> stated that the library software stands out as one of the central elements in the process of automating a library. A computer lacking software is comparable to a library without both librarian and books, rendering it incomplete and ineffective. The libraries of all types must embrace the ongoing challenge of adopting new technologies if, they want to continue serving as information providers for higher education institutions. Moreover, the use of software's for automation is very crucial to handle the explosion of information in libraries of all types <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Hassan, Hamid &amp; Shah, 2022)</ref>.</p><p>Among the key technologies crucial to the functioning of libraries include the integrated library system (ILS) that manages library collections and services. Whereas, the digital library is responsible for organizing and maintaining digital assets like institutional repositories. There are several commercial options available for these systems, the growing need for technology coupled with limited budgets has sparked a mounting interest in OSS within academic libraries. Unlike proprietary software, OSS is characterized by developers' permission to create derivatives from the original software, free distribution and modifiable source code <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Choi &amp; Pruett, 2015)</ref>. In other words, the open-source software refers to computer software with source code that is accessible under a license or arrangement, such as the public domain, allowing users to study, modify, and enhance the software. Furthermore, it grants the freedom to redistribute the software in its original or modified form. OSS is commonly developed in a joint venture within a public context. It represents a prominent model of open-source development and is often likened to user-generated content <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Randhawa, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>It is a fact that the information professionals are operating in a more complex yet fascinating environment. Their ability of providing effective services depends on leveraging open and concealed digital resources on the internet, which poses a challenging task for library professionals. Modern libraries continually strive to innovate and offer a diverse range of services to users with the aid of information and communication technology (ICT) applications. OSS has gained widespread popularity in current times, with libraries around the world extensively adopting it. Academic libraries are increasingly turning to Open Source Software (OSS) to cut costs, break free from vendor lock-in, and most significantly, offer users tailored technology solutions. While existing research primarily focuses on well-known OSS products through case studies and anecdotal evidence, this research provides more comprehensive and widely applicable insights for US academic libraries considering OSS adoption, based on an online survey reported by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Choi, &amp; Pruett, (2019)</ref>.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Rafiq (2009)</ref>, OSS refers to computer software whose source code is available under a license that permits users to use, modify, improve, and distribute the software, either in its modified or unmodified form. The access to a program's source code empowers developers to enhance and fix any aspects of the software that may not be functioning optimally. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Reddy and Aswath (2015)</ref> are of the opinion that currently, numerous open-source computer applications are available to libraries for tasks such as library automation, management of library websites, knowledge management, and digital library administration. They also said that opensource software has gained popularity within the library environment, leading to a significant migration of libraries embracing the open-source software movement. They also found that a vast range of open-source software and applications, each with unique features and functionalities, are available for automating library tasks and operations. Examples of library software include Dspace, GSDL, e-Prints, Koha, Joomla, ABCD, Drupal, NewGenlib, and many more, all facilitating efficient and continuous information services to library clients.</p><p>In connection to the technological developments in Pakistan the utilization of computers in libraries have commenced during the late 1990s, with the assistance of the Pakistan Scientific and Technological Information Center (PASTIC) being recognized as the first institution to employ a computer for their union catalogue of scientific periodicals <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Haider, 1998)</ref>. Then Rafiq and Ameen in 2010 discovered that Information technology (IT) has significantly enhanced library services in Pakistan. They found that three libraries in Pakistan were using the Koha software, and 47.8 percent of librarians expressed interest in adopting Koha. The first instance of Koha being implemented in Pakistani libraries was in 2006, as reported by Ur Rehman, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mahmood, &amp; Bhatti, (2012)</ref>. As noted, that integrated library systems (ILS) are largely absent in Pakistani libraries; however, the usage of OSS, notably the Koha ILS, is on the rise in Pakistan. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Rafiq and Ameen (2010)</ref> further revealed that, presently the OSS, particularly Koha, has gained immense popularity, primarily due to its free availability and distinguishing features, not only in developing countries like Pakistan but abroad as well such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Moruf, Sani, and Abu (2020)</ref> stated that the main reason of adoption and usage of Koha in Nigerian libraries is a result of its distinguishing features.</p><p>The attitude of librarians towards IT revolutions means a lot in the successful provision of services to library users, therefore technology adoption attitude of librarians needs to be explored <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Shehzad, Tariq, &amp; Naeem, 2021)</ref>. In another study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Khan (2020)</ref> expressed that Pakistani librarian demonstrated hesitancy when it comes to embracing digital innovations, often relying on traditional practices. Such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Rafique, Subhpoto, &amp; Idrees (2023)</ref> found that in the academic libraries of Sindh province Pakistan, majority of the services and functions were not fully automated. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ahmad &amp; Ahmad (2017)</ref> stated that university libraries in Peshawar are using Information Technologies but not adequately. In other study, also found that developing countries like Pakistan faces many challenges with OSS documentation and support <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Rafi et al., 2019)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Jabeen et al. (2018)</ref> reported that plenty of interest among librarians in OSS existed, but the lack of in-house training and expertise blocked its adoption. Similarly, substandard OSS code and lack of internal trained staff was an issue for U.K. libraries <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Dalling &amp; Rafferty, 2013)</ref>. However, recognizing the significance of OSS (like Koha and other library software's) as a valuable opensource software for library automation, these researchers have suggested its adoption due to practicality, user-friendliness, cost-effectiveness, and ease of maintenance. Acknowledging the importance of Koha, it becomes crucial to understand the drivers and obstacles influencing its </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Objectives</head><p>Most basic objective of adopting OSS in libraries is to enhance overall efficiency and quality of library services. The below are some of the relevant objectives associated with the current topic of the study: 1. To ascertain the commonly used open-source software in libraries of Pakistan. 2. To gain knowledge about the reasons for the adoption of OSS, specific modules of OSS, OSS suitability to libraries, the level of satisfaction from OSS by the library staff and the impact of software's on the library functions, and challenges being faced in the implementation of OSS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Questions</head><p>The following questions are outlined to reach the set objectives.</p><p>1. Which types of library software's are they using? 2. What are the causes behind the implementation of OSS in libraries? </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method employed in this study</head><p>The quantitative design using an online survey was considered appropriate for the study.</p><p>The target population was comprised of all the librarians employed in public and private sectors universities and colleges, across four provinces of Pakistan. The instrument designed with the help of previous literature was used to gather data online from the respondents through purposive sampling technique. The sample included all those librarians who were using OSS in their libraries.</p><p>The questionnaire was distributed using SurveyMonkey, an open-source tool that provides visually appealing templates for creating both structured and unstructured questionnaires. Respondents were able to access the questionnaire conveniently through a simple link. The decision to employ an online questionnaire is driven by the goal of reaching a wider audience of potential respondents.</p><p>The questionnaire consisted of two sections, addressing various aspects including demographic information, and the adoption of OSS including the reasons of adoption, module beneficial ness to library community, satisfaction levels with the OSS, challenges encountered when using OSS, and recommendations regarding OSS adoption etc. To ensure the validity of the draft questionnaire, two experts in the field of library and information science reviewed and approved it for the research. In July 2023, the questionnaire was distributed online to librarians working in colleges and universities through multiple platforms such as WhatsApp, Facebook, Twitter (Now X), email, and SMS along with the request that library professionals using OSS in their libraries should respond. Ultimately, 251 questionnaires were returned by respondents from diverse locations across Pakistan. The data was coded and fed in SPSS software for analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Finding Response Rate</head><p>The instrument was distributed online in July 2023 through WhatsApp, face book and other social media to reach the sample that was geographically spread over the research site as well as to get a good response rate. A total of 251 responses were received that is a fair response for the analysis of the situation regarding the adoption of OSS in Pakistan.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background Information</head><p>The data in table 1 shows that more than half of the libraries 54% are medium in size, some 26% libraries are large in size and only 20% libraries are small. When respondents were asked about the familiarity with OSS, data shows that, 2% respondents expressed that they are not familiar with OSS, 34% are somewhat familiar, and 64% are familiar and very familiar.</p><p>The responses regarding the number of professional staff involved in operating OSS show that majority 118(47%) of the libraries using OSS are having more than 6 professional staff whereas, in 75(30%) libraries there are 4-6 professionals working and about 58(23%) libraries the professional staff was up to 3 members. So, for the types of software are concerned no library was using commercial software, majority 128(51%) of the respondents are using free software, 70(28%) are using Open Source software and only 53(21%) have adopted home developed software's. Similarly, when the subjects are asked whether they are trained to use software's or not. A large majority143 (57%) said that they are partially trained and 45(18%) state that they are fully trained. Surprisingly, 63(25%) mentioned that they are using software's without training.</p><p>It is very encouraging that a large majority of the respondents are familiar with OSS and most of the libraries adopted OSS are medium or large in size. Small libraries are rarely adopted OSS. Similarly, majority of the libraries using OSS are having staff not less than 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background Information</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Variables</head><p>Categories Frequency Percentage Size of Library Small Libraries 50 20% Medium Libraries 136 54% Large Libraries 65 26% Familiarity with OSS Not Familiar 5 2% Somewhat Familiar 86 34% Familiar 100 40% Very Familiar 60 24% Professional Staff involved in using OSS 1-3 58 23% 4-6 75 30% More than 6 118 47% Type of Software use in library Commercial 0 0% Home Developed 53 21% Free 128 51% Open Source 70 28% Staff training Not trained 63 25% Partially trained 143 57% Fully trained 45 18% Adoption of Open-Source Software</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Types of OSS adopted in Libraries</head><p>The detail about the different OSS used in the libraries shows that majority 151(60%) of the libraries are using Koha, followed by SLIMS that is used by 33(13%) and 24 (10%) libraries using GREENSTON and 13(5 %) DSpace. However, 30 (12%) libraries in Pakistan using other software's.</p><p>It shows that Koha, SLIMS and GREENSTONE are the highly used software's as compared to DSpace and In-House software's. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reasons for the Adoption of OSS</head><p>The table <ref type="table">3</ref> shows the answers regarding the reasons for the adoption of OSS. It reveals that cost saving, customization and security are the major reason with highest mean score, 4.34,</p><p>In order to determine the modules which are more beneficial for the library community, the study participants rated the below mentioned modules in their softwares. The data in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">5</ref> shows that library professionals are of the opinion that the following modules of OSS like, Cataloguing (mean=4.02), Circulation/Patron management (mean=4.00) and Digital Library Management (mean=3.99) the most beneficial to their community. However, some modules like, OPAC mean=3.89, Search mean=3.79, Book reservation mean= 3.78, Acquisition mean=3.76 are less beneficial to the library patrons. In addition, they stated that, OSS module i.e. Inter-library loan mean=2.97 has the lowest advantage for the library users.</p><p>The findings shows that all modules of OSS are beneficial with different mean scores but, among these cataloguing, circulation and digital library management are very important than serial management, acquisition and inter-library loan. The extent of customization of your OSS to meet your library's specific needs</p><p>The respondents were asked to express their view about the customizability of their OSS used in their library. The details in table 6 reveals that more than half of the respondents 136(54.18%) agreed that their software's are highly customizable. Another larger group of the respondents 92(36.65%) said that their software's are moderately customizable. But, a reasonable number 23(9.16%) mentioned that their software's are customizable. Thus, it is good that the larger group expressed that they have adopted OSS which are highly or moderately customizable which can be used to meet the specific need of the community.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 6</head><p>The extent of customization in Open Source Software (OSS) to meet library's specific needs</p><p>S. No The Ability of customization in your OSS Frequency Percentage 1. Not customizable 23 9.16% 2. Moderately customizable 92 36.65% 3. Highly customizable 136 54.18% Total 251 100% Scale: 1-3, 1 Not customizable and 3 Highly customizable.</p><p>How satisfied are they with the adoption of Open Source Software?</p><p>The adoption of OSS in libraries affects the respondent's level of satisfaction The tabulated data in table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">7</ref> shows that, the library professionals are satisfied with the highest mean score=4.56 and highly satisfied with the second highest mean score, 3.65. However, they are very dissatisfied or dissatisfied with the lowest mean scores as, 2.67 and 2.01.</p><p>Here, it is important to note that some of the respondents give no opinion regarding the satisfaction The challenges faced by the librarians in the adoption and implementation of OSS So, for the challenges faced by the librarians in adopting OSS are concerned? The respondents' answers have been displayed in table 8. It discovers that, the most important challenges in adopting OSS are; Lack of technical expertise mean score=4.76 followed by two challenges, lack of planning and security concerns having same mean scores=3.99 are considered as important by the respondents. The rest of the challenges mentioned by the respondents like, Compatibility issues with the existing systems mean=3.02, lack of internet mean=2.10 and lack of Hardware mean=2.13 are considered less important by the study participants. Findings showed that lack of technical expertise is the biggest problem in the adoption and implementation of OSS. Would you recommend the adoption of OSS to other libraries in Pakistan? In response to this question, about 221 respondents said that yes, they would recommend other libraries to adopt the OSS because of the following reasons. 1. Open-Source Software (OSS) are user friendly as mentioned by 199 2. Open-Source Software (OSS) are customizable as mentioned by 168 3. Open-Source Software (OSS) are providing Cloud as mentioned by 155</p><p>Remarkably some 30 respondents gave no answer regarding the recommendation of adopting OSS in libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitation and delimitation of the study</head><p>One of the limitations of the study is that researchers is not able to find the exact number of libraries using OSS which could be used for data collection. However, it is decided to distribute the instruments online and wait for three months in order to get maximum response. After the specified time 251 responses were received, data was fed in the SPSS for further analysis.</p><p>Similarly, the study is delimited to the academic libraries (College and Universities libraries) both in private and public sector. It does not include data from the Public, Special or National libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions and Recommendations</head><p>The In light of the data analyzed and findings drawn, following recommendations are extracted for future applications.</p><p>1. As a smaller number of small libraries are adopting OSS as compared to medium and large libraries. Therefore, authors recommend all sizes of libraries to adopt the OSS to improve library services and to enjoy the cost saving in developing country like Pakistan where there are economic challenges faced by the academic institutions.</p><p>2. As Koha, the highly used and followed by SLIMS, GREENSTONE and DSpace software's, therefore, training programs regarding these software's should be arranged by the LIS schools and Library Association to highlight these software's among library professionals.</p><p>3. The library software's are mainly adopted for its cost saving and customization facilities therefore, this research strongly recommends that LIS curricula has some courses on programming which can enable the system librarians to install, customize, use and maintain the software's and hardware. Learning these skills and techniques librarian should be able to overcome the technical challenges related to OSS.</p><p>4. As this study found that librarians are very much sure that OSS are suitable because of open-source code, variety of its modules and due to its easy installation. But, at the same time they expressed that the cataloguing, circulation and digital library management modules are more beneficial to library users and in addition they also stated that lack of planning and technical expertise and security concerns are the main hindrances in the way of OSS adoption. Therefore, the researchers suggest that to enhance the knowledge of librarians related to OSS trainings, workshops and conferences should be organized on different levels.</p><p>5. Respondents revealed that they are satisfied or highly satisfied with OSS because of its user-friendly interface, customizability therefore, they recommend other libraries in the country to adopt Open-Source Software's. Keeping in view the satisfaction of the respondents with the OSS this study also recommends the adoption of OSS but, after proper planning and prior feasibility study.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>acceptance and rejection within the Pakistani librarian community. Additionally, considering the prevailing gap in literature regarding the adoption of innovations among Pakistani librarians, there is a potential for research focusing on identifying and validating the factors that determine the intention to adopt OSS in libraries. Similarly, in Pakistan the Pakistan Scientific and Technical Information Center (PASTIC, 2017) has played a pioneering role in introducing cloud computing to the field of library and information sciences in Pakistan. The utilization of cloud computing began with the implementation of Pak-Cat, which served as the union catalogue for Pakistani books. This initiative was carried out as part of the larger project titled "Modernization of PASTIC National Science Reference Library with Effective Resource Sharing," dated 2-08-2017. To cater to local requirements, PASTIC customized the Koha library automation software in collaboration with Pakistani library professionals. In this regard, PASTIC organized a meeting of library professionals under the Consortium of S&amp;T and R&amp;D Libraries of Pakistan on October 18th, 2017, where the decision was made to proceed with the customization. At present, a total of 162 libraries in Pakistan are using the PASTIC Koha cloud. The open-source software paradigm has brought about a significant shift in the software development landscape, fundamentally changing how software is designed, developed, and disseminated. Its numerous advantages make it particularly appealing for libraries, especially those in developing countries. While the use of Open Source Software (OSS) is on the rise in Pakistan, proprietary software remains dominant; however, the open-source movement has made significant strides in various industries, including government, education, and libraries, gaining considerable momentum and influence. Challenges such as the availability of technical expertise, resistance to change and limited awareness about open-source alternatives may have influenced the pace of adoption in certain sectors however, this research is intended to investigate the present scenario regarding the adoption of OSS in the libraries of higher education throughout Pakistan.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>3. How suitable is the open-source software for your library's needs? 4. Which module(s) of the open-source software are the most beneficial to your library community? 5. How much customizable are the open-source software's to meet your library's specific needs? 6. How satisfied are they with the OSS they are currently using? 7. Are there any challenges encountered in the adoption and implementation of the OSS? 8. What recommendations would you provide to other libraries contemplating the implementation of OSS solutions? Significance of the Study The financial challenges arising from the COVID-19 pandemic have resulted in budgetary limitations for organizations, including libraries. Consequently, there has been a notable increase in the use of open-source software (OSS) in libraries to effectively manage budget constraints. By utilizing OSS, libraries can prioritize crucial areas such as collection development, staff training, and enhancement of user services. The flexibility and customization options provided by OSS allow libraries to tailor software to their specific requirements, creating an individualized and efficient environment that seamlessly integrates with existing infrastructure and operational processes. The collaborative nature of OSS promotes cooperation among libraries and organizations, enabling the exchange of ideas, software development contributions, and the utilization of collective expertise to improve software solutions. Adopting OSS provides libraries with autonomy from specific vendors, granting them greater control over their technology infrastructure. Furthermore, OSS emphasizes security and reliability, benefiting from community scrutiny and adherence to open standards, thereby promoting interoperability and preventing reliance on proprietary formats. By embracing OSS, libraries can encourage innovation and adaptability, stay abreast of technological advancements, and effectively respond to evolving user expectations. While challenges may arise during OSS adoption, understanding and addressing these challenges allows libraries to develop effective strategies for successful adoption. Proper planning, stakeholder engagement, staff training, and ongoing support are crucial factors in maximizing the benefits of OSS in library environments. Overall, the adoption of OSS in libraries provides a cost-effective solution to optimize budget allocation, foster collaboration, and promote innovation, thereby enhancing services, improving user experience, and positioning libraries at the forefront of technological advancements in the evolving library landscape.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>study investigated the adoption of Open-Source Software (OSS) in libraries in Pakistan, revealing a significant shift towards OSS adoption. A majority of libraries (54%) are medium in size, and most librarians (64%) are familiar with OSS, with Koha, SLIMS, and GREENSTONE being the most commonly used OSS. The reasons for adopting OSS include cost savings, customization, security, and community support, indicating a growing recognition of OSS as a viable alternative to proprietary software. Despite the challenges faced by librarians in adopting OSS, including lack of technical expertise, the majority of respondents (221) would recommend OSS to other libraries in Pakistan due to their user-friendly nature, customizability, and cloud-based services. The study concludes that OSS have the potential to revolutionize library services in Pakistan, and libraries should invest in training and technical support to fully harness the benefits of OSS. The study recommends prioritizing OSS adoption in libraries to enhance library services and promote digital literacy in Pakistan, aligning with the global trend of embracing open-source technology in libraries.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The Types of OSS used in Libraries</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">S. No Open Source Library Software</cell><cell cols="2">Frequency Percentage</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Koha</cell><cell>151</cell><cell>60%</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>SLIMS</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>13%</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>GREENSTONE</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>10%</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>DSpace</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>5%</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Other</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>12%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>251</cell><cell>100%</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Module(s) of the open-source software most beneficial to you and your library community</figDesc><table><row><cell>S. No Modules of OSS</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Respondents level of satisfaction with the adoption of OSS</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">S. No Respondent's satisfaction level with the adoption of OSS</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>SD</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Very Dissatisfied</cell><cell>2.67</cell><cell>1.230</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Dissatisfied</cell><cell>2.01</cell><cell>1.034</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Neutral</cell><cell>3.56</cell><cell>.990</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Satisfied</cell><cell>4.56</cell><cell>.011</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Highly satisfied</cell><cell>3.65</cell><cell>.988</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Scale: 1-5, with 1 being l very dissatisfied and 5 highly satisfied.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The Challenges faced by the participants in the adoption and implementation of OSS</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">S. No Challenges faced in the implementation of OSS</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>SD</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Lack of planning</cell><cell>3.99</cell><cell>.763</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Lack of technical expertise</cell><cell>4.76</cell><cell>.001</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Compatibility issues with the existing systems</cell><cell>3.02</cell><cell>0.999</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Security concerns</cell><cell>3.99</cell><cell>.277</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Lack of Internet</cell><cell>2.10</cell><cell>1.231</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Lack of Hardware</cell><cell>2.13</cell><cell>1.171</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Scale: 1-5, with 1 being low and 5 being high.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>4.01 and 3.54 respectively. The other minor reasons for the selection and adoption of OSS are community support mean=3.23 and compatibility with existing systems mean=3.01. The analysis of data in table below shows that they adopt library software mainly for its cost saving and customization facilities rather than other reasons. The suitability of OSS for library's Need</p><p>In order to know the opinions of the respondents' regarding the suitability of OSS for their libraries are displayed in table 4. The respondents expressed that OSS are suitable due to its features like open source code having highest mean score, 4.55 and the variety of modules having the second highest mean score 4.01 along with easy installation and customization mean=4.00.</p><p>The other suitability is OSS features and functions mean=3.90 and easy understanding mean=3.24. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Status of ICT in the University Libraries of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pakistan Library and Information Science Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developing of Institutional Repository in Public Sector University Libraries of Punjab, Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Asad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Management and Practices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Librarians&apos; perceptions about adoption and uses of the Koha integrated library software in Punjab</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Asim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Mairaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/EL-11-2018-0224</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/EL-11-2018-0224" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pakistan. The Electronic Library</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="624" to="635" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The characteristics and motivations of library open source software developers: An empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pruett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.lisr.2015.02.007</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lisr.2015.02.007" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library &amp; Information Science Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The context and state of open source software adoption in US academic libraries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pruett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/LHT-02-2019-0042</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/LHT-02-2019-0042" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library hi tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="641" to="659" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open source, open minds: An investigation into attitudes towards open-source library management systems in UK higher education libraries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Program</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Library automation in Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Haider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Information &amp; Library Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open-Source and Proprietary Library Automation Software: A Comparative Academic Librarian&apos;s Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hamid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Management and Practices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of Smart Technologies in University Libraries of Pakistan: A Qualitative Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/libphilprac/6055" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">6055</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and Practice (e-journal</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Library professional&apos;s opinion about open source software adoption: Status, problems and measures used in libraries of Beijing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jabeen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qinjian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jabeen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Knowledge, Memory and Communication</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>China</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating the Factors Influencing Librarians&apos; Intention toward the Adoption of Koha-An Open Source Integrated Library System in Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/libphilprac/4360/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library Philosophy and Practice (e-journal)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open Source Automation Software: Stirring Automated to Integrated Library System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moruf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Abu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Sciences and Environmental Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1273" to="1278" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The current state of library open-source software research: A descriptive literature review and classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/LHT-05-2013-0056</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/LHT-05-2013-0056" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library Hi Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Library Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pastic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://consortium.pastic.gov.pk/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-12-19">2017. 19 December, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pastic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://consortium.pastic.gov.pk/Koha" />
		<title level="m">Koha (Open Source Library Software) Cloud</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-12-19">2023. 19 December, 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIS community&apos;s perceptions towards open-source software adoption in libraries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rafiq</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Information &amp; Library Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology integration for students&apos; information and digital literacy education in academic libraries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rafi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jianming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/IDD-07-2019-0049</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/IDD-07-2019-0049" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Discovery and Delivery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoption of open-source software in Pakistani libraries: a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rafiq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ameen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Age</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploration of ICT Applications in Public Sector University Libraries of Interior Sindh: A Mixed Methods Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rafique</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Subhpoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Idrees</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Management and Practices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modernization of central library and establishment of an e-resource center at Chittagong Veterinary and Animal Sciences University (CVASU): A Case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1108/LHTN-06-2016-0029</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1108/LHTN-06-2016-0029" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library Hi Tech News</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Library Professionals Participation and Contribution to Koha Open-Source Software Used in Libraries of Public Sector Universities of Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rahoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Business Education and Management Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Open source software and libraries . university of Arizona</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Randhawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://repository.arizona.edu/bitstream/handle/10150/105743/Open_Source_Software_and_Libraries.pdf?sequence=1" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open Source Software&apos;s in Libraries: Threats and Challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Aswath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Library and Information Studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigating Technology Adoption Attitude among Public &amp; Private Sector University Librarians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shehzad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tariq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Naeem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Information Management and Practices</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Free and open source software movement in LIS profession in Pakistan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ur Rehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mahmood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bhatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/libphilprac/852/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Library Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">852</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and Practice (e-journal</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
